So today we pick up on the bottom of למד ד' Dalet
*Lamed Daled*, we'll see if we can also get through למד ה'
*Lamed Hey*, but we're at the bottom of למד ד' עמוד א'
*Lamed Daled Amud Aleph* in מידות Midot *Middot*. And we are on...
we did the שבעה שערים *Shiva Shearim*, yeah I think we're on
ה' *Hey*, so we'll pick up on ה' *Hey*. So we were
listing the various places which, you know, I don't know, we'll read
ד' *Daled*, I don't remember anymore. Okay, yeah, we had just finished
ג' *Gimmel*. We had spoken about the gates of the הר הבית
har habayit *Har HaBayit* and now we're moving on to the gates
in the עזרה Azarah *Azara*. By the way, it did say that
the gate in the east they would use to go to the
הר המשחה *Har HaMishcha*, הר הזיתים *Har HaZeitim* for the פרה אדומה
*Parah Adumah*, and I pointed out that the reason the main entrance
wasn't in the east is because the east opens up to the
Kidron Valley, which is this huge drop-off, so you can't access it.
Well, if you can't access it, how do you get out of
it to the הר הזיתים *Har HaZeitim*? So I thought I remembered
Michael might have mentioned it here, but I double-checked the משנה Mishnah
*Mishnah* in פרה *Parah* that actually says they built a bridge, Michael
mentioned it, Michael mentioned it, they built a bridge, כבש היו hayu
לו lo *keves hayu lo* from הר הבית Har Habayit, *Har HaBayit*
to הר הזיתים *Har HaZeitim*. They built a bridge to span the
valley, span the Kidron Valley, to get them from הר הבית Har
Habayit. *Har HaBayit* to הר הזיתים *Har HaZeitim*. I don't know if
it was a permanent bridge or if it was a temporary one,
but they did, the few times they had the פרה אדומה *Parah
Adumah*, but that's how they actually did it.
They also did that to avoid any טומאה *tumah*. Right, the way
they built it.
Right, exactly. There's a description of how they built it to avoid
טומאה *tumah*, but the fact, so they built it in a way
to avoid טומאה *tumah*, but the reason they needed it was because
you can't, you know,
whatever, you can't really get there, the incline is so steep. But
all of that is why the entrance was not to the east.
Yeah, I don't know, you know, the other thing is if the
incline is so steep, how do you build a bridge? But the
Romans figured that out, right? That was the way the Romans won
a lot of their wars, is that they were able to cross
rivers that couldn't be crossed because they figured out how to engineer
a bridge across a river when you were only on one side.
It's brilliant. I can't figure out how you can do something like
that, but anyway, you start on one side and you build the
bridge across the river. Wow. So anyway,
so yeah, but so I don't know the exact number, I mean
maybe it was, that's why I said maybe it wasn't a permanent
one, maybe it was like a rope bridge, but yeah the description
in פרה *Parah* doesn't sound like that exactly, but a rope bridge
might be.
Yeah, I got
this impression of these big stone vaults.
Yeah, that's the way it's described, so I don't really get it.
Okay, moving on.
And that Kidron Valley, by the way, was also where the water
that took the blood and stuff out of the בית המקדש Beit
HaMikdash. *Beit HaMikdash* would empty into. Okay, now ד' *Daled*. שבעה שערים
היו בעזרה *Shiva shearim hayu ba'azara*, so there were seven gates in
the עזרה Azarah *Azara*. We had discussed this part of this when
we were in תמיד Tamid, *Tamid* when we were discussing where the
כהנים Kohanim *Kohanim* would walk. So there were seven gates in the
עזרה azarah *Azara*. שלשה בצפון ושלשה בדרום *Shlosha batzafon ushlosha badarom*, three
in the north, three in the south. ואחד במזרח *Ve'echad bamizrach*, and
one in the east. שבדרום *Shebadarom*, the ones in the south: שער
shaar הדלק *Sha'ar HaDelek*, I mean if you've got your picture from
right at the beginning, the picture that had everything labeled, where did
I put that? Here, this
one.
Michael's, Michael's has the picture. And anyway, I know though, there you
go. So there's שער shaar *Sha'ar*, so we're in the south. Okay,
so שער הדלק *Sha'ar HaDelek* is...
I know, it's not exactly the same number. The גמרא Gemara, *Gemara*
already said there were debates exactly what it was.
And they think in which picture
you also use, it's a little bit different. All right, everybody, what,
nobody has the actual photograph, everybody is estimating. Okay, שער הדלק *Sha'ar
HaDelek*. Now דלק Delek, *Delek* obviously means like fuel, so the assumption
is that this was where, and this is where the חידוש *chidush*
is, thinking this through, I always assumed they basically stored stuff in
these rooms, but this is a gate, it's a gate going to
the outside. They didn't just store the firewood in this room, this
was like deliveries in the back. Okay, where are you getting the
firewood into the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash? *Beit HaMikdash*? You're not taking
it through
the front gate.
I don't know, I think that's also where they de-wormed the wood,
but that's not where they got the delivery of the wood. You
know, maybe they, I'm not exactly sure. I know, so who knows?
I don't know, but anyway the basic point so is that they
are getting from, you're not going to take the various materials you
need through the front door. So you're getting from this gate, you're
getting the wood. That's the שער הדלק *Sha'ar HaDelek*. It's actually also
interesting because the picture that you have here does not have that
it then has an opening
into the עזרה azarah *Azara*, it just has an opening to the
outside. So maybe it's even possible that they stored the wood here
and then when they needed it, they took it out of here
and they brought it through a different one of the gates, like
the שער העליון Sha'ar HaElyon? *Sha'ar HaElyon*, or maybe then they did
bring it through the עזרת נשים Azarat Nashim, *Ezrat Nashim*, but this
picture at least shows only an opening to the outside.
Why? It doesn't have an opening to the inside.
Because if you look at the בית המוקד Beis ha-Moked, *Beit HaMoked*,
there's like a broken line where because the בית המוקד Beis ha-Moked
*Beit HaMoked* we know did have an opening into the
עזרה Azarah *Azara*.
But anyway. The oil?
The oil?
But what did they use oil for? They only used oil for
the מנורה. Menorah. Oh, that's interesting. I bet.
Yeah, but then you wouldn't call it דלק, Delek you wouldn't call
it fuel. But maybe for instance this way דלק is gas, you
know, if you.
I understand. No, you wouldn't call it that for the oil about
the מנורה.
Maybe that drawing's something, because every gate has that rectangular thing.
Yeah, it could be
some kind of a raised portion or something, you know, where there's
still an entrance under. You know what I mean? Like.
Yeah, yeah, I guess.
I mean,
look, the other thing is that the thing, according to the גמרא,
Gemara the לשכות Lishchos only, their קדושה Kedushah was determined by where
their opening was. According to this picture, I should have checked, I
didn't, according to this picture all of the openings were to the
חול Chul or off of the מקדש Mikdash grounds, which would mean
that they would be חול, Chul, but if you remember it also
said that the לויים Leviyim were on the outside of these because
they couldn't sit on the inside. So that suggests that they were
קודש. Kodesh. So I'll have to figure that out. But anyway, it
is, so whether it also had an opening on the inside, I'm
not sure, but it is, but I think it's important to realize,
to think that this might be about how you get this stuff
from the outside of the מקדש Mikdash into the מקדש. Mikdash. So
you had, let me read a few more. So you have the
שער דלק, Sha'ar Delek, שני לו שער הקרבן, Sheni Lo Sha'ar HaKorban,
then you had the
שער הקרבן, Sha'ar HaKorban, שלישי לו שער המים. Shelishi Lo Sha'ar HaMayim.
Now if you see there's a ד by קרבן, Korban, a lot
of the גרסאות Girsos have שער הבכורות, Sha'ar HaBechoros, the firstborns, right?
So that also could be. I mean, why would you store your
firstborns there if they were coming in the main door? So what
it actually could be is it's a quick drop-off, you know, like
they have at the library, you just drop off your books so
you don't have to wait in line or whatever. You know, so
like or they used to have the deposit things when when you
had these drive-by banks before you actually everything was ATM, you know,
you just drop it off. So here I am, I have my
בכורות, Bechoros, right? I want to deposit them maybe and move on
with my day.
So maybe so you you give the בכור Bechor there and then
they'll come and they'll collect them when it's the right time. This
is where you drop off the בכורות. Bechoros. Another explanation by the
way why it was here was it was also to the south
of the מזבח Mizbeach and therefore בכורות Bechoros don't have to be
in the north, they're קדשים קלים. Kodashim Kalim. Now you could say
well why not all שלמים? Shlamim? Well, could be because בכור, Bechor,
the כהנים Kohanim gets to eat it, so it could easily be
confused with קדשי קדשים, Kodshei Kodashim, which also כהנים Kohanim eat, although
this כהנים Kohanim could eat it, you know, in all ירושלים, Yerushalayim,
so maybe they בדווקא Bedafke had it in a place in the
south. So this was the שער הבכורות. Sha'ar HaBechoros.
And then where are we? שלישי לו שער המים, Shelishi Lo Sha'ar
HaMayim,
the third one was the gate of water. Why the gate of
water? Because this is where they would get water when they were
doing the ניסוך המים Nisuch HaMayim later משנה's Mishnah, going to say,
you know, they did a whole ritual, so they brought the water,
you know, in through here and then they're going to do a
ניסוך המים Nisuch HaMayim on the מזבח, Mizbeach, which by the way
also shows that there were openings on both sides. You know, you
have to bring it from the outside and then there's a way
to get it from that room into the
inside for סוכות, Succos, yeah, for סוכות. Succos. And it's not, again,
it's still not exactly clear to me because the גמרא Gemara makes
a big deal of where the openings were and it seems like
all of these to be functional you're going to want to have
two openings. Maybe there's like a main opening and a tiny little
backdoor, you know, or something. Anyway,
so what's the שער העליון? Sha'ar HaElyon. What is the, is that
where they went out, right? They went out by the שער העליון.
Who? When? What are you asking? What is it? Oh, what is
it?
Oh there, it's mentioned yet. Because it's mentioned these.
Yeah, I have to double check. Right, this has more than is
mentioned in our משנה, Mishnah because the גמרא Gemara already said that,
you know, sometimes five, sometimes seven, sometimes thirteen. Is that exactly clear
how many?
I remember the five, the seven.
Anyway, there's a debate exactly how many. Okay, it doesn't matter.
I thought the high one was seven.
No, the גמרא Gemara mentioned early, even a תנא Tanna that says
more. Okay, now, that's, those are the three on the
south. שבמזרח, SheBaMizrach, in the east, שער ניקנור, Sha'ar Nikanor, which is,
if you look, that the main entrance to, like this 3D picture
says, this is really brings it up. It's this, after the עזרת
נשים, Azarat Nashim it is the main way, the front door for
everybody that's coming from the outside, all ישראל Yisrael into the עזרה
Azarah, proper. Okay, the עזרת נשים Ezras Nashim is essentially like the
social hall, the ante, you know, the waiting room, and then this
is the main door into the עזרה Azarah. proper. It was called
ניקנור. Nikanor. The גמרא Gemara, tells a story about, right, that he
was the person that was bringing these big brass doors from Alexandria,
I believe, and then there was a whole storm, it was like
a יונה Yonah story, and he threw one of the brass doors
over, hoping that it would make because it was the weight, and
then the storm was still going, and he said throw me over
with the brass door, and a big whale came, no. So then
the storm stopped because, and then, and then when they got when
they docked they found the other brass door was right, was attached
to the hull of the ship. Anyway, so they named the gate
after him. So that's שער ניקנור. Sha'ar Nikanor. ושתי לשכות היו לו,
U'Shtei Lishchos Hayu Lo,
there were two little rooms. chambers off the side of this gate.
מימינו, mimino, אחת מימינו ואחת משמאלו, achas mimino ve-achas mismolo, one on
the right, one on the left. אחת לשכת פנחס המלביש, achas lishkas
Pinchas hamalbish, one was called פנחס Pinchas the dresser. He apparently was,
we mentioned before although last time we mentioned it we said that
was taking place in the לשכת הגזית, lishkas ha-gazis, but here was
the פנחס Pinchas who apparently helped the כהנים Kohanim take off and
on their clothes. Maybe he didn't do it there, maybe that's where
he stored his stuff, maybe that's where he waited until he was
needed. Okay, but anyway he was the one that helped the כהנים
Kohanim on and off with their clothes.
That's bizarre. Right. ואחת לשכת עושי חביתין, ve-achas lishkas osei chavitin, and
the other one was where they made these חביתין chavitin for the
כהן גדול. Kohen Gadol. Yeah, that's right. Okay, so we had mentioned
that already. Now, but we didn't mention the chamber. Now, ושבצפון, ve-she-ba-tzafon,
in the north, continuing here clockwise, שער ניצוץ, Sha'ar Nitzotz, the one
in the, except now we're going from sort of to the, whatever,
the north, but we're starting at the back, at the west. So
of the spark, not exactly clear what that was, again some say
it was to bring a, made a fire to add to the
מזבח mizbei'ach because you're supposed to bring your own fire, not just
have the fire that's already there. כמין אכסדרה היה, ke-min achsadra hayah,
and it was like a, we had mentioned this already in תמיד,
Tamid, it had like a type of a אכסדרה achsadra which is
like a portico or at least it was like two columns with
a roof on the top of them and the כהנים Kohanim were
watching from the top of this portico or from the top
of this, what do you call it, from this type of a
balcony.
That might be what's in all the other diagrams, Andy, because...
Oh I see, that's a good point. If you look at the
pictures, they all have like these columns and those are to indicate
the אכסדרה. achsadra. That's a very good point. Of course it's funny
that it points it out דוקא davka here, you know, and not
other ways, but right, you're probably right that it's in addition to
the gate, you had some type of a thing with columns and
a thing on top that people were standing on.
Which is why you're not seeing, it doesn't look like an entrance
to it, but maybe underneath that, you know, in other words, underneath
this might
be some kind of a, oh I see, so what you're saying,
that could be, okay, that's an interesting point. All right, so anyway,
ועלייה בנויה על גבה, ve-aliyah benuyah al gabah,
there was a balcony or something on top of it, a platform.
ושהכהנים שומרים מלמעלה, ve-she-ha-Kohanim shomrim mil-ma'alah, the כהנים kohanim would watch above,
והלויים מלמטה, ve-ha-Levi'im mil-matah, and the לויים Levi'im below. So David is
right, it's interesting that they had that structure at least in this
diagram on all of them, because this emphasizes it by this שער
הניצוץ. Sha'ar ha-Nitzotz. ופתח היה לו לחיל, u-pesach hayah lo la-chel, and
it had an opening into the, into the חיל. chel.
We read that with none of the others.
I know, and I was looking in the מפרשים mefarshim about that.
The חיל chel is, you see it says on this picture, החיל.
Ha-Chel. The חיל chel is this like buffer space which is, there
was like a little, a small like sort of wall, not really
a wall, like, like sticks or whatever, fence around like, you know,
a buffer zone before you actually got into the עזרה azarah proper
and the space between the fence and the חיל, chel, which was
like ten אמה amoh wide, about fifteen feet wide, was the space
between that and the עזרה azarah, was called the חיל. chel. Okay,
that was like that buffer zone. So here it says there was
an opening into the חיל chel and I completely agree with Michael,
I read this and I said, woah, every, all these things had
an opening, that's how you got there from the outside, and I
looked in the מפרשים, mefarshim, I could not find anybody that addressed
that question. Many, I'm sure somebody does, I'd have to look further.
Was this the boundary for the
non-Jews, the חיל?
chel? The non-Jews can't even go into the חיל, chel, I believe.
I believe the non, yeah, I believe part of the purpose of
the סורג soreig is, just to double check some משנה Mishnah, in
כלים, Keilim, but yes, I believe that's correct, they say can't even
be in the, in the חיל. chel. And then the difference between
who can be in the חיל chel and who can be in
the עזרת נשים Ezras Nashim, might have to do with טבול יום
Tevul Yom and טמא מת. t'mei meis.
So yeah, there is a, I think non-Jews definitely cannot be in
the עזרת נשים, Ezrat Nashim. I believe, if I'm remembering correctly, they
also cannot be in the חיל. chel. That's correct. Okay, so,
okay, where are we? שני לו שער הקרבן, sheni lo Sha'ar ha-Korban,
now the second one was the שער הקרבן, Sha'ar ha-Korban, now if
you look at our picture it's בית הניצוץ, Beis ha-Nitzotz, בית המוקד,
Beis ha-Moked. but in the בית המוקד Beis ha-Moked. you had the
thing for the sheep, for the תמיד, Tamid, the טלאים, tela'im, which
is a chamber there, and so therefore the gate was called the
Gate of the הקרבן, Korban, because within that room you would bring
the קרבנות korbanos every day for the תמידים. temidim. So that's what
at least the name of the gate was called. שלישי לו בית
המוקד, shelishi lo Beis ha-Moked, and the third one was called the
בית המוקד. Beis ha-Moked,
Yeah, one minute, hold on a minute,
because the שער הקרבן Sha'ar ha-Korban wasn't the בית המוקד. Beis ha-Moked.
One minute.
Yeah, this picture that we're looking at is not exactly reflecting. Yeah,
this picture, if you look at the picture on the other side,
right, so it actually has, meaning the other side, it has first
another gate, this מ"ב mem-beis number before you get to מ"ג. mem-gimmel.
So מ"ב mem-beis was the שער הקרבן, Sha'ar ha-Korban, according to this,
was the שער הקרבן, Sha'ar ha-Korban, not, no, no, you flip it,
right, it does not have the next one was בית המוקד, Beit
HaMoked. the next one was this, and this is שער הקרבן, Sha'ar
ha-Korban, well why ever it's called שער הקרבן Sha'ar ha-Korban I don't
know, and then the third one was בית המוקד. Beit HaMoked, So
not what I said a minute ago, which was, you see little...
prints on there.
Yeah, I know, this it calls it שער הקרבן. Shaar HaKorban. Right,
שער הקרבן Shaar HaKorban also.
But it's
not following exactly this משנה, Mishnah because this משנה mishnah, has another
one first which is called שער הקרבן, Shaar HaKorban, and then the
third one is בית המוקד. Beit HaMoked. All right. So anyway, a
little confusion there. Moving on.
Okay, so let's take a look.
Okay. ארבע לשכות היו בבית המוקד. Arba lishchot hayu b'Beit HaMoked. Now
there were four chambers in the
בית המוקד, Beit hamoked כקיטונות הפתוחות לטרקלין, kikitonot haptuchot latraklin, like little
chambers that open up into like a big castle. שתיים בקודש ושתיים
בחול. Shtayim bekodesh ushtayim bechol. Two in the sanctified, in the עזרה
azarah. space, and two in the, and two outside. And again, according
to the גמרא, it's because there was
openings, there's an opening into the עזרה, azarah, and there's an opening
outside. So therefore, half of it was קודש, kodesh, half of it
was חול, chol, and you drew a line in the middle.
וראשי פסיפסין, Veroshei pispasin, and here it is, מבדיל בין קודש לחול.
mavdil bein kodesh lechol. The tops of the פסיפסין pispasin would distinguish
so you would draw the line between the קודש kodesh and the
חול. chol. Now what's the ראשי פסיפסין? roshei pispasin? So some say
it means that these were basically beams coming out of the walls,
so basically the beams protruded a little in the walls, so you
would sort of see, you know, you'd see the beams and you'd
say, okay, that's the line. But the Albeck has an interesting explanation
because he says פסיפס pispeis means, it certainly means in modern Hebrew
mosaic. When they talk about finding ancient mosaics, it's פסיפס. pispeis. So
he actually says that they would have like a different mosaic, you
know, on the floor to distinguish, or, or maybe the mosaic would
begin or something to distinguish between which was the קודש kodesh and
which was the חול. chol. Okay. ומה היו משמש? Umah hayu meshamesh?
What did they use these chambers for? מערבית דרומית, Maaravit dromit, southwest,
which is, anything in the south here is going to be in
the קודש. kodesh. So southwest, היא הייתה לשכת קרבן, hi hayeta lishkat
korban, you see, or some say טלאי קרבן, t'laei korban, so you
see this confusion. That was the chamber of the קרבן, korban, but
anyway, or some say it's לשכה lishka of the sheep of the
קרבן, korban, meaning that's the chamber where they checked the תמידים temidim
for four days before taking them out to bring them as a
קרבן. korban. דרומית מזרחית, Dromit mizrachit, southeast, again in the קודש, kodesh,
היא הייתה לשכת לחם הפנים. hi hayeta lishkat lechem hapanim. That's where
they would bake the לחם הפנים. lechem hapanim. It was a very
hot room, they had a big fire, they would bake the לחם
הפנים. lechem hapanim. מזרחית צפונית, Mizrachit tzonit, the northeast, again going clockwise,
now we're in the חול. chol. בו גנזו בית חשמונאי את אבני
מזבח ששיקצום מלכי יוון. Bo ganezu Beit Chashmonai et avnei mizbe'ach sheshiktzum
malchei Yavan. That's where when they, when, when the חשמונאים Chashmonaim were
victorious in the time of חנוכה, Chanukah, right, that they, and they
had to, their various stones that was seen that the יוונים Yevanim
had defiled the בית המקדש. Beit HaMikdash It's a question, how do
you defile the בית beit המקדש? But anyway, a separate discussion. But
therefore, they tore down these stones off this מזבח mizbe'ach and they
buried them there, they stored them there. Now in another place it
says that that was actually called the place of לשכת חותמות, lishkat
chotamot, that's what we had in תמיד, Tamid because if you needed
your, you brought your קרבן korban and you needed your נסכים, nesachim,
you would go by that door, you would basically give them money,
they'd give you a פתק, petek, חותם, chotam, a receipt, as it
were, a קופון, kupan, and then when you were bringing your קרבן,
korban, you'd hand the כהן kohen this קופון kupan and they would
know you have paid for it and then they would bring, you
know, you know, bring the נסכים nesachim for you, the מנחה mincha
and the נסכים. nesachim.
Why not just have a box for everything else? What? Just put
your money in the box.
I'm sorry, what are you asking?
When you do the birds or whatever, you just
throw your money in the box. Oh, yeah, why didn't you do
that? That's a good question. Maybe because if it's the birds and
there's money in it and there's a fixed price, you know, oh,
you mean...
That's an interesting question. I'm not sure. Maybe there was, because there
was different prices based on what type of...
Maybe more of a thing that you need a receipt for the...
Well, because you also have to buy the right ones. It's a
good question. But I assume it's because you've got, because, hmm, I'm
get-, I would guess because there's different amounts, right? If you have
a sheep or a goat or a cow, it's different amounts. So
if you have money in a box and there's a fixed price
for birds, you know, oh, I've got $100 here, that's 100 birds.
But if you've got $100 here, how many נסכים nesachim is that?
You have no idea, right? Because there's different prices. Of course, you
could say well why not have three boxes? So I don't exactly
know the answer to that. Okay.
Yeah, I guess the final thing I could say to answer that
question is, is that if you don't bring your קרבן korban you
don't bring your קרבן, korban, that's sort of your business, if you
didn't put your money in there, I mean not your business, but
you know what I mean, it's like whatever. But if you're bringing
your sheep, we want to make sure it's being done right. So
we want to make sure that the נסכים nesachim are coming with
it. So if you're cheating and not putting in the money for
the נסכים, nesachim, you're sort of implicating us by bringing your sheep
without the נסכים. nesachim. So I would guess it's something about like
that.
What?
So they want to check that you paid.
Exactly, exactly. Okay. צפונית מערבית, Tzonit maaravit, and how about the northwest?
בה יורדים לבית הטבילה, Bah yordim l'beit hatvilah, that's where you would
go to go to the מקווה, mikveh, and you know we had
discussed a כהן kohen that would become טמא tamei in the middle
of the night, he would sleep there, he would go down there
and go to the מקווה. mikveh. Okay? Turning the page
now, ל"ז עמוד ב', Lamed Zayin Amud Bet,
משנה ז'. Mishnah Zayin. שניים שערים היו לבית המוקד. Shnayim shearim hayu
l'beit hamoked. There were two gates to the
בית המוקד. beit hamoked אחד פתוח לחיל ואחד פתוח לעזרה. Echad patuach
l'cheil ve'echad patuach l'azarah. One to the חיל cheil and one into
the עזרה. azarah One guesses, I haven't seen it, but one guesses
that the word חיל chel is ultimately a play on the word
חול, chol, but you don't actually want to call הר הבית Har
Habayit חול, chol, but you're emphasizing that it's not actually the עזרה
Azara. per se. Okay, so one entering into the קודש kodesh and
one entering into the חיל. chel. אחד פתוח לעזרה. Echad patuach l'azarah.
אמר רבי יהודה, Amar Rabbi Yehuda, זה שהיה פתוח לעזרה, ze shehaya
patuach l'azarah, the one that opens up into the עזרה, Azara, פשפש
קטן היה לו, pishpash katan haya lo, there was a tiny little
door inset into this big gate, שבו נכנסים לבלוש את העזרה. shebo
nichnasim livlosh et ha'azarah.
You would go in there, but פלטי paltei means like out there,
you would go out from that door in order to scout out
the עזרה. Azara. If you remember we learned in תמיד Tamid that
early in the morning, or actually I'm not sure if we actually
described what happened, but we quoted this משנה, mishnah but presumably one
of the כהנים kohanim went out there and scouted out. What was
he scouting out? Maybe he was the one scouting out to make
sure that the כהנים kohanim were on their jobs being שומר, shomer,
but the explanation that's given is that he was just checking to
make sure like all of the כלים keilim were put away and
everything was taken care of, the whole was ready for business for
the next day. Okay, so now משנה ח. mishnah chet. בית המוקד
beit hamoked, כיפה. kippah. So this בית המוקד beit hamoked had a
dome on top. ובית גדול היה, uveit gadol haya, and it was
a big chamber, big house literally. מוקף רובדים של אבן, Mukaf revadim
shel even,
and it was surrounded by stone steps. So what does that mean?
Were there stone steps on the inside, were there stone steps on
the outside leading up to it? It sounds like on the inside
although it says מוקף, mukaf, surrounded, but maybe it means in the
interior because of the next line, וזקני בית אב v'ziknei beit av
and the picture probably shows it that way, וזקני בית אב ישנים
שם, v'ziknei beit av yeshenim sham, and the elders of the בית
אב beit av of that day's work would sleep there. Now what
does there mean? It could mean there in the whole בית beit
המוקד, hamoked. but we learned in תמיד Tamid. that actually all the
כהנים kohanim, would sleep in the בית beit המוקד or at least
the ones that were working the next morning of the בית אב.
beit av. So some say it means no, they would sleep on
the top of the steps or that the steps would lead to
little sort of like carved out chambers in the wall and the
זקנים zkenim would sleep there. Okay, I assume that's got to be
the hottest because heat rises so it's the warmer. Okay. ומפתחות העזרה
בידם, Umiftechot ha'azarah beyadam,
they had in their hands the keys to the עזרה, Azara, okay,
because it gets locked up at night. We're going to talk about
it being locked up and it could only be opened from the
inside. So you needed somebody on the inside to let you in.
Okay, so therefore they were the ones on the inside sleeping and
they had the keys. ופרחי כהונה איש כסותו בארץ, Upirchei kehunah ish
kesuto ba'aretz, and here it speaks about the other כהנים, kohanim, the
young כהנים, kohanim they would not be up there on the top,
they would all be sleeping on the ground with their garments. And
again, does that mean that they would sleep on their בגדי כהונה?
bigdei kehunah? Can you get benefit from בגדי כהונה? bigdei kehunah? That
was a discussion we had in תמיד. Tamid. So this was a
little echoing back to תמיד. Tamid משנה ט. Mishnah tet. ומקום היה
שם אמה על אמה. Umakom haya sham amah al amah. Now it's
going to tell you where the keys were stored. There was a
place there, an אמה amah by an אמה, amah, like a foot
and a half by a foot and a half, וטבלא של שיש
v'tavla shel shayish and it was apparently like some type of a
thing built on the ground or whatever and there was a big
marble cover to
it, טבלא, tavla, big marble cover to it. היתה קבועה בה, Hayeta
kevuah bah, was fixed on top
of this platform, a low platform an אמה amah by an אמה.
amah. ושלשלת של מפתחות היו תלויות בה Veshalshelet shel maftechot hayu tluyot
bah and the three keys were hanging from it. Okay, from it
sounds like from it, does it mean, like it was like a
big chamber on the ground and there were three keys in the
chamber and there was this marble cover to it, or were the
keys hanging from the marble cover itself? Okay, the grammar could sound
like it anyway, but they were hanging from the cover itself. שלשלת.
Shalshelet.
Mine says שלשלת. shalshelet.
No, we're about to get to שלשלת. shalshelet. Until now we've done
של שיש. shel shayish. Okay, first it was out of marble, we
haven't gotten to the word שלשלת shalshelet yet. Oh, שלוש. shalosh. We're
about to get to it. Did I say שלוש? shalosh? Anyway, I
meant שיש. shayish. Okay.
No, oh. ושלשלת של מפתחות, Veshalshelet shel maftechot, I'm sorry, you're right.
No, no, you're absolutely correct. I misread that. You are correct. So
there is a, thank you, a chain, thank you, a chain of
holding onto the keys. היו תלויות בה Hayu tluyot bah were suspended
from it. He's right, not שלוש. shalosh. Excuse me, yes. So there
was a chain. So again, is it was like here's I've got
this big marble cover and I put it on top of something
and then I pick up the marble cover. Is there now in
this thing a chain holding the keys like a keychain? Or is
it like somehow the chain is coming off of the marble cover,
I pick up the marble cover and the chain is there? But
you're right, chain, I'm sorry, I misread that. But again, it's a
little bit unclear like why what's the idea of storing it in
a place where I guess you can't misplace your keys if you
have a whole big place, but
it's not like it further locks them up. Maybe it's like a
little hidden
away, so anybody who doesn't know, the משנה Mishnah is telling us,
but anybody who doesn't know wouldn't know where to find them. It's
not exactly clear why you had this structure. What?
Too late for us by now. Too what?
Too late, too late for us. Now they can give away the
secret. It's like when you have it like under the rock, right?
Maybe that's where. What? Two פ, peis, by the way. Two what?
Two פ? peis? Two פ peis for us. Now they can give
away the secret. It's like when you have like, you know, under
the rock, right? Maybe that's what it is. So you have it
in this like little sort of מרמור marmor thing, but you lift
up the marble thing, and there, and there's, and there's, and there's
the chain with the keys.
Okay, so thanks.
What was the ceremony, and this was his boss?
Right, you're probably right, probably make it more ceremonial. Yeah.
So when he gets his חותם chotam for נסכים, nesachim, he takes
it to where?
He takes it back. He takes he goes when he's bringing his
קרבן, korban, he takes it with him.
No, he gets the and where's the ממונה memuneh on נסכים? nesachim?
Oh, so he has this receipt.
They handle it. They have a whole thing.
And he goes from one side of the לשכה lishkah to the
other?
No, he gets his חותם chotam there, he comes out here, he
comes through the main gate, he brings his קרבן, korban, the כהנים
kohanim say, let me see your פתק, petak, he gives them the
פתק, petak, and then the כהנים kohanim take the oil and whatever
they need.
So someone probably on oil duty?
Exactly. Okay, back to this. ושלשלת veshalshelet של shel המפתחות hamaftechot היו
תלויה tluya בה, bah, and a chain with the keys were hanging
by it. הגיע higia זמן zman הנעילה, haneila, now we're going to
talk about the locking up, because in תמיד Tamid. we talked about
them opening up, and so the time of locking
comes, הגביה higbia את et הטבלה, hatavla, you lift up this marble
cover, וטבעת vetabaat בה, bah, רגע, rega, sorry, how do you lift
up a marble cover? So there was a ring on top of
it, you know, that you could grab onto, at the top of
the cover. What? So much for the secret, I guess. Right. Okay,
though maybe that was the trick. There was a ring hidden somewhere
else, and you had to get the ring and attach it to
the cover, I don't know. Okay, with a ring, ונטל venatal את
et
המפתחות hamaftechot מן min השלשלת, hashalshelet, you took the keys from the
chain, ונעל, venaal, and then you locked up all the doors from
the inside. הכהן hacohen מבפנים mibifnim ובין uvein לוי Levi ישן yashen
לו lo? מבחוץ. mibachutz.
So the כהן kohen we had mentioned just earlier, the כהנים kohanim.
walked on the inside, and the לויים Leviyim on the outside. Now
again, ישן yashen לו? lo, I mean, what type of, you know,
again, we had talked before maybe you could sit, but you sleep?
I mean, what type of guard duty is it if everybody's asleep?
How symbolic, how purposeful is that? So someone switched the גרסה girsa
from ישן yashen to ישב yashav לו, lo, which fixes it. But
again, it's certainly curious that some have this גרסה girsa of ישן.
yashen. It could mean he could, some, he would sometimes fall asleep.
Why would you describe it that way? Anyway, we're going to let's
finish this משנה Mishnah and then you'll ask me. Okay. גמר gamar
מלנעול, milinoal, you finished locking, החזיר hechzir את et המפתח hamafteach לשלשלת
lashalshelet ואת ve-et הטבלה hatavla למקומה, limkomah, you put the keys back
on the chain
and the הטבלה hatavla back in its place, the cover back in
its place. נתן natan כסותו ksuto עליה, aleha, now you put your
garment on top of it, וישן veyashan לו, lo and he slept
on it. So the person who's in charge of the keys actually
sleeps on top of the box. Okay? So just make sure that
nobody else gets access to the keys, you're sleeping on top of
the box. Now of course this is a little funny because, you
know, משנה ח chet said זקני ziknei בית beit אב av were
on top of the steps and מפתחות maftechot העזרה haazarah בידם, beyadam,
they had the מפתחות maftechot in their hands, right? And then this
says that the מפתחות maftechot were inside of this box and presumably
it was on the floor and somebody was sleeping on top of
that. So who was holding on to the keys? Was it the
זקני ziknei בית beit אב av with in their hands up at
the top or was it somebody on the floor sleeping on top
of there?
Just maybe in case the guys from outside needed to get in.
They were all on the inside. All this was taking place inside
of here. So you know, right inside of the בית המוקד.
The guy, I thought we said maybe the guy's on watch on
top of the building? Oh yeah, so that'd be outside the building.
You mean if somebody needed if somebody needed a key
and you don't want to wake up the person sleeping on the
bottom to get the keys? I don't know. It sounds like they're
describing
unless somehow you try to conflate these two, that the people sleeping
on top is the זקני ziknei בית אב av and that this
marble thing is on top. There's a way to conflate the two
and say that we're talking about not the floor, we're talking about
and בידם beyadam doesn't literally mean בידם, beyadam, it means that they're
on top of this. But again, it is a different description.
Okay.
אירע ira קרי keri באחד beechad מהם, mehem, it sounds like we're
no longer talking about the זקני ziknei בית אב, av, we're talking
about the כהנים. kohanim I mean, not that that couldn't happen, but
anyway, the classic description here is the כהנים Kohanim on the floor.
One of them had a nocturnal emission which we discussed in תמיד.
Tamid. יוצא yotze והולך veholech לו lo במסילה bimsilah המהלכת hamalechet תחת
tachat הבירה. habirah. He went with the roundabout or whatever that went
underneath the בירה, birah, whether that refers to the מקדש Mikdash as
a whole or just one section of the מקדש. Mikdash. ונרות venerot
דולקים dolkim מכאן mikan ומכאן, umikan, and the lights were lit up,
the, you know, the underground passageway. עד ad שיגיע sheyagia לבית le-beit
הטבילה, hatvilah, until he came to the place where he could actually
go into the מקווה. mikvah. רבי אליעזר בן יעקב Rabbi Eliezer Ben
Yaakov, אומר omer במסילה bimsilah המהלכת hamalechet תחת tachat החיל hachayil יוצא.
yotze.
He no, he went in a different type of a tunnel, not
one that went either deeper or more under the מקדש, Mikdash, but
actually that went towards the outside underneath the חיל, chayil, leaving the
עזרה Azara, grounds. והולך veholech לו בטדי. be-Tadi. And here it tells
you that this שער טדי Tadi which the earlier one said, right,
was not used for anything, it was used for something. It was
used for when the כהן kohen had to leave in the middle
of the night, this was called שער טדי. Tadi. Okay, so he
would leave here in the north, and as I mentioned yesterday, some
say that the word should be טרי tari that the Aramaic טרי
tari means like private and that this was the private gate he
would sneak out. But that's his
opinion with that's the... so again notice רבי אליעזר בן יעקב, Rabbi
Eliezer Ben Yaakov he's almost like the only תנא Tanna mentioned in,
you know, who's not having a halachic opinion but a description about
what happened. So again the assumption is and of the בבלי Bavli
and ירושלמי Yerushalmi that רבי Rabbi אליעזר Eliezer בן ben יעקב Yaakov
was the author of תמיד. Tamid. Anyway so he says as opposed
to the idea that he stayed there, he came back and waited
till morning and we didn't ask him to leave in the middle
of the night, he says no actually they did ask him to
leave in the middle of the night and he went and he
went out. Did he not go to the מקוה Mikveh first? No,
it sounds like no. It says no, he just says he left
as soon as possible. Go to the מקוה Mikveh when you get
outside of הר הבית, Har Habayit? but don't stay here any longer.
Okay, so very interesting different take than we had when we learned
that in
תמיד.
Tamid By the way, I wanted to say based on this picture
that you don't go out in and then give you a receipt,
looks like you go from one side of this to the other.
Here you give the money, then you go to the other side
and you give it and you just take from that person and
then you get the נסכים. Nesachim. This is the way they conceptualized
it.
And why is that more I guess because one person doesn't have
to work with the money? It's sort of like when you go
for your what do you call it? When you go for your
driver's license, right? You go on one line and you pay, isn't
there something? Like there's a different line when you pay and then
you go to the other place and they process it or whatever.
Maybe. Okay, I mean that makes sense. But then the idea of
חותמות Chotamot is just not like its main function, it's just like
an efficiency and this is really the place where you buy your
נסכים. Nesachim. Yeah, okay that could be, that could be.
It's just that it's much more I
actually imagine it as much more efficient the way I described it
because the כהנים Kohanim? have all of the oil, all of the
whatever, let them handle it. You just give them the coupon.
So where
is, you know in the New Testament like when Jesus is railing
against all the money changers, where were all those people?
Yeah, that's a good question.
Some think we're talking about things like this? Well, it could also
be that there was a whole
business, look at these, remember for anybody who's seen that, this year,
Robinson's Arch, this is you know whatever, you know when you go
and you visit, this is you see what's left here of the
Robinson's Arch.
So anyway, so they would enter here. But you know if you've
ever taken that tour, they say people would be walking on the
outside and there'd be all these little
shops and maybe what they'd be buying birds, maybe they'd be buying
the animals, maybe they didn't want to do the coupon, maybe they
wanted to buy their own נסכים. Nesachim. So I
imagine, because this isn't the entrance, all of that business or whatever,
some of it is on the outside, it's actually on the west.
The entrance was on the south. So you know, it could have
been that. I mean I don't know, but you'd have to reread
the story for a little more descriptive where it happened.
Where is the Cardo? Is that what they say it was? Little
shops?
Right, but here too they say this thing of the Robinson's Arch,
they say that what they would have shops that would be lining
the outside. Where the stairs go? Yeah, yeah exactly.
What's this long building on the end?
In that reimagining? I don't know. I
think oh yes, I think they even found some archaeological stuff about
that, that when they would go up שערי חולדה, Shaarei Chulda, they
wouldn't, they'd go first up into this sort of like just a
nice little shaded area, you know, before they then walked into the
open עזרה. Azara. Not עזרה, Azara הר הבית. Har Habayit? You know
what I mean? Like sometimes you go up, like now I'm thinking
about all my Israel experiences, like I remember when you go to
the top of what do you call it, מצדה, Masada, right? First
thing you get out, there's like a whole little shaded area before
you walk, anyway whatever. That's anyway but I think they actually did
find like some stuff that's into that. I don't think it's described
in any of the משניות. Mishnayot. Okay. Someone told me once that
the סנהדרין...
Sanhedrin... What? Someone told you what?
Someone told me once that's where the סנהדרין Sanhedrin was. Yeah, yeah
that is, I mean certainly not what חז"ל Chazal think. חז"ל Chazal
think that again, oh you know what maybe it's also based on
some descriptions in the Gospels, I don't know. But as far as
I know that is not described in any of the משניות. Mishnayot.
And as far as the סנהדרין Sanhedrin at least as far as
חז"ל Chazal understand, that was in the
לשכת הגזית, Lishkat HaGazit, which was right there in the עזרה. Azara
I mean it was, where was it? It's right here, right? It's
where they did the lottery, it's half in the עזרה, Azara that's
where the סנהדרין Sanhedrin was according to
חז"ל. Chazal. So yeah, but I think that's like a Christian interpretation.
Okay, so anyway move on.
All right.
מידות פרק ב Perek Bet משנה ד Mishna Dalet עמוד ב Amud
Bet second
paragraph. הר הבית היה חמש מאות אמה על חמש מאות אמה. Har
Habayit hayah chamesh me'ot amah al chamesh me'ot amah. So the entire
הר הבית Har Habayit? was five hundred by five hundred אמה, amah,
which is whatever seven hundred fifty feet by seven hundred fifty feet.
So here's a picture of it. When it's that exact, you would
assume that it's somewhat of a rounding, okay, because you can make
a building very exact, you can't make a mountain very exact. Unless
it means that the wall they made around it was seven hundred
fifty by seven hundred fifty since I decided where you're making the
wall. Right, is that what
you were saying? 500 אמה amah which is
like 750 feet. 500 אמה amah which is like 750 feet.
It's about two blocks.
Is it? How much? Two blocks is 750 feet?
Let's see. 20 blocks in a mile, roughly.
So 20 blocks in a mile. Mile is like 5000 and change,
so it's 250 feet to a block. So it's three blocks, three
city blocks.
Three city blocks. Doesn't seem so big, I mean, I know you
look up at it, but...
It's a square, space-wise as the city, it's huge. Aha. 3, 4,
5...
Except,
you know, a bit...
Okay,
but this is a modern picture. I don't... Is that wall...
No, with the...
I see that, but what we're seeing at the top of the
hill, was that wall? Is that the whole הר הבית? Har Habayit?
I guess so, we normally assume it is.
Yeah.
Three square city blocks? I would say so. Is
that
the whole הר הבית?
Har Habayit Yeah.
In that
picture.
Yeah. Okay, but this is about how much it was. Smaller than...
What? It's smaller than Central Park.
Right. Well, Central Park is a lot more than three city blocks.
Okay, anyway. All right. רובו מן הדרום, Rubo min hadarom, most of
it in the south, right, it wasn't centered as you see in
this picture. Most of the space was in the south. Now remember,
people came in the south. So you want, I think, a big
space, like a buffer zone for people to mill around and to
collect and so on, right? So the most of the space is
in the south. שני לו מן המזרח, Sheni lo min hamizrach, the
second largest space here was in the east. שלישי לו מן ה...
Shelishi lo min ha... where was it? שלישי לו מן הצפון, Shelishi
lo min hatzafon, then the north, each one of these strips is
getting smaller, and
מיעוטו מן המערב, Miuto min hamaarav, and the very smallest amount was
in the west. מקום שהיה רוב מידתו שם היה רוב תשמישו, Makom
shehayah rov midato sham hayah rov tashmisho, they would give bigger space
where they would use... where it would be used more. Now, what
does used more mean? So some actually say that there were not
mentioned here structures that actually, you know, and there were more structures
here than there were. But that sort of still begs... A, it's
interesting to think that although we look at this and we say
it's all, you know, it's all open, maybe there were some structures.
But the question still is, well, why were most people using things
here? So certainly why you were... why you needed more space in
the south is clear. Why after that to the east? I would...
I would imagine is because what's going to happen? You have to
go into the east, right? So you come up the south, and
as we said, that was because the city was built to the
south and the slope was to the south. You need... you want
a nice big mall and space and yard to mill around and
to שמוז shmooze with all your friends and whatever, right? So that's
the big... then everybody moves to the east. So the east still
has to be pretty large and you come into the east. Okay,
and then maybe, I don't know, you had to go and get
your חותם chotam and your נסכים nesachim and anyway, maybe you were...
you were walking around and looking. But the west, you didn't want
really too many people there, that was behind the קודש קדשים, Kodesh
Kodashim, and that was the space that was very minimal. So that's
really why it's aggregated that way. Now we face the... I'm sorry,
not the west, I'm sorry, I said the west, I meant the...
yeah, the west, the west, right, you're right. The west, yeah. So
right, it is true, the כותל Kotel is now behind the קודש
קדשים. Kodesh Kodashim. But we're outside. Yes, okay. But right... right next
to the...
closest to the center... to the קודש קדשים. Kodesh Kodashim.
Yeah,
that's what I just said. That's why you wouldn't want people... it
would be inappropriate to have people milling around behind the קודש קדשים.
Kodesh Kodashim. You don't have...
you don't have moneychangers on הר הבית? Har HaBayit. I'm sorry? You
don't have moneychangers on הר הבית?
Har HaBayit Yeah, they could have been. What were they changing money
for? Maybe because you had to go buy your נסכים, nesachim, maybe
because you had to go buy your sheep, but where were they
selling sheep? So you know, again, it does not sound like they
were selling sheep up at the top. But they said רוב תשמישו.
rov tashmisho. Could there... could there have been places around here in
the הר הבית Har HaBayit itself in this big west space where
they were selling sheep and they were the moneychangers and who knows?
It could very well be, I don't know.
Okay,
all right.
Is this where the moneychangers were?
Yeah, right. So that was the question, where was that taking place?
Okay. Yeah, anyway if you look at this picture, right, you can
sort of see the similar proportions. I mean here you certainly see
a big space to the south. It's a little bit skewed in
the perspective based on the angle of the picture, but this is
a lot... I know, but this is a real one, not a...
not an... I'm saying, but you see, you know, you see it's
not centered. Okay, anyway. So that had to do with how they
used it because as I said, they came into the south and
then they moved from the south around to the east.
משנה ב. Mishnah bet.
Never pass a fire code.
What? Never pass a fire code.
Zone one means entry. They're... they're stone. No fire escape.
No, there's not one means of entry, there are... there are five
gates. But there's... but
the west was...
No, but for the average, for non-Kohen,
no, everybody was allowed around at all places. I mean, they didn't
want, I think, a lot of people in the west, but you
were allowed, you were allowed to use the other gates.
And the women had separate entrances into?
Well, that's the עזרת
נשים.
Ezrat
Nashim. No, they didn't have a separate entrance in. Everybody had to
go through the עזרת נשים. Ezrat Nashim It's not like, it's not
like on these פרום frum weddings, like the men go in this
door and the women go in that door.
I imagine families being separated.
Yeah, they were separated because the women stayed behind in the עזרת
נשים Ezrat Nashim and the men went in with the.
If they didn't have cell phones, right? And a mob scene, the
women have to be in the behind and the men go forward
with all the men, how do they, you know, how
are they going to reconnect?
Reach each other at home
at twilight.
Right.
Well, home could be, yeah, two days away.
I don't know. I mean, it's also interesting, how much do we
assume that they went up, men and women, you know, families together?
You know, the man was the one bringing the קרבן. korban. I'm
not saying women didn't go.
And he thought she wasn't breathing, so they went together.
Right, right, right, but I'm just saying if, you know, because as
the sort of simplicity in your question and as implicit from the
fact that there was an עזרת נשים Ezrat Nashim. as opposed to,
you know, to the other to the main עזרה, Azara the women
were not the primary bringers of the קרבן, korban, the primary people
that were present for the קרבן. korban.
But if someone gave birth,
she would be the one to physically be bringing it.
But they were there. I agree they were there as much as
the
men were there.
Maybe more because women had
to, had obligations, right?
Yeah, yeah,
all these gates were locked until the people in the.
Yeah, it never says about the gates of, oh, the gates of
the עזרה. Azarah.
No, I mean, we're talking about the keys that are held by
the, right? So does that mean everything else is locked and then
they go around and open all the gates?
Yes, and that's what we learned in תמיד with a lot of
order that how they opened it in the morning. Here we're going
about the locks. No, you're right, רבקה. Rivka. I just, okay, it's
an interesting thing to speculate later.
Is the fact, ideally I had assumed that because there was so
little space in the עזרה Azarah proper and the עזרה azarah. proper
was for, you know, although women were allowed and could come when
they were bringing a קרבן, korban, you know, the emphasis was certainly
male, you know, and that's why there's this עזרת נשים. Ezrat Nashim
I assumed that that women would often, you know, it's like.
Wait, you say the emphasis was male. No, I don't, I don't
agree with that. Women could bring their קרבן. korban. The כהן Kohen
had to come and get it from the woman somehow,
but there were probably as many women there as men.
Right. But you know in שול shul that very often a wife
will ask her husband to, in a lot of שולן, shuls, to
say a מי שברך Misheberach for, you know, or to to do
the baby naming or whatever.
But you gave the case of the woman who's born bringing the
קרבן korban after לידה. leida. Yeah, the woman had to bring herself.
Yes, but she didn't have to personally be present.
Because she had to bring it. She could just send it with
somebody.
Yeah, you could send somebody to bring your קרבן. korban. The only
reason you would have to personally be present is if you had
to do סמיכה. semicha. And that's the issue of whether women had
to or had the option of doing סמיכה. semicha. That's that's the
question. And you don't do סמיכה semicha by birds. So if the
קרבן, korban, so sometimes the יולדת yoledet was a bird and a
sheep, but it could be two birds. And if it was two
birds, which seems like it was quite often, most people didn't have
the money for the sheep, then there would be no סמיכה. semicha.
So that's what I'm saying. I imagine that the the whole sort
of system, you know, was very male-oriented like our שולן shuls are
and that's why, you know, women would sometimes come into the men's
section but primarily be out.
No, I think there's no reason to think that. We know from
the story of.
Then why is there an
עזרת נשים Ezrat Nashim that
is not the עזרה Azara proper?
On פסח Pesach the women had to eat from קרבן פסח Korban
Pesach just like the men. I get it, so פסח Pesach we
can assume there were full number of women, right?
Yeah, but not everybody of a group would bring the קרבן פסח.
Korban Pesach. You could have ten people in a group and one
person would bring it.
But they needed to eat it.
They had to eat it. Yes, but where they're eating it is
off הר הבית. Har HaBayit They're eating in ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Everybody came
to ירושלים. Yerushalayim. Everybody is in the city. Okay, it's a רגל.
regel. But who's going up to הר הבית Har HaBayit, and getting
into the עזרה Azara and actually handing the קרבן korban over to
the כהנים? Kohanim So if what you were saying was correct, I
would assume what you're saying is correct if you did not have
a major division here between the עזרת נשים Ezrat Nashim and the
עזרת ישראל. Ezrat Yisrael.
So the women stayed in the.
To me, what that says is the women stayed in the עזרת
נשים Ezrat Nashim or maybe they even stayed at the bottom of
הר הבית Har HaBayit and the men went in with the קרבן
korban and maybe with their wives' קרבן. korban. That's how I imagine
it.
But the women's space was bigger, right?
Because the women's was the lobby. So you know, the everybody's. Everybody
is there in the lobby, men, women, and children. Everybody is there
waiting for their turn. So one group and then it's my turn,
now I'm going to go and I go in. But the reason
it said נשים Nashim is primarily to indicate some ראשונים Rishonim think
that women would not be allowed allowed in the עזרת ישראל. Ezrat
Yisrael. But that is not correct and תוספות Tosafot makes the point
that that's not correct. But still the framing that as עזרת נשים
Ezrat Nashim, seems to say that they were
not it was not primarily their space.
I'm not trying to say I like it, I'm just trying to
say that's the sense one gets.
I understand, but I'm disagreeing with you on your concept that there
were mostly men there because it seems to me from the sources
mostly men in the עזרת ישראל Ezrat Yisrael and an equal amount
of men and women.
I get it. So women might have been on the הר הבית
Har HaBayit. with their right. I get that. They're in עזרת נשים,
Ezrat Nashim. they're on the הר הבית, Har HaBayit. yes, I would
agree, and even because you have a huge עזרת נשים. But actually
bringing the קרבן Korban into the עזרת ישראל, Ezrat Yisrael, that I
don't know. Okay, fine. All right, let's move on.
Where are you going out? You said how are they going out?
Who's going out?
Whoever it is that went in.
Yeah, the same source.
They go in, go through this way, and when they go out
where do they go out?
Same way presumably, yeah.
What about this פסוק Pasuk in יחזקאל? Yechezkel?
I don't know, please, please. Okay, now, so now we're actually going
to read that.
כל הנכנסים להר הבית נכנסים דרך ימין. Kol HaNichnasim LeHar HaBayit Nichnasim
Derech Yamin. Whoever would go into the הר הבית Har Habayit? would
go would turn towards the right as we said. You go up,
there's a huge space on the south and then you move towards
the entrance which is towards your right, which is the east, which
also supports the whole approach that you're always moving counterclockwise and you're
moving towards your right. ומקיפין ויוצאין דרך שמאל. UMakifin Veyotzin Derech Smol.
Now here it says that they
would they would circle around and go out on the left. Now
if you read it that literally it sounds like right it sounds
no, not שער התדי Sha'ar HaTadi because primarily presumably the שערי חולדה
Sha'arei Chulda served for in and out. It means that you would
pass actually behind the back of the בית המקדש and go out.
So it would be like a traffic circle, right? You come in
on this one, you circle around and you go out on the
other one and תוספות Tosafot says that could very well be except
that that would be interesting that it would require everybody to do
a whole sort of סיבוב, Sivuv, although actually you know it is
kind of funny and it is then funny that you have such
a narrow space whatever, but maybe again people would spend they would
leave by drips and drabs they would come in maybe more at
once.
Also they walk out one of these other.
Well, that's what I was asking. No no no no, they didn't
go into the עזרה. Azara They only went into the first eleven
אמות. Amot. They only went into they went in, they gave their
קרבן, Korban, they turned around.
But what about this gate here?
Yeah, that gets them out of the עזרה Azara, but it doesn't
get them out of הר הבית. Har Habayit We're talking about how
they get out of הר הבית. Har Habayit Right, and they didn't
go... Oh, you're saying, but wait, which gate did you just show
me?
Well if you don't have a side. I was thinking here, here.
They can go
in here, go in this and go out a
side gate towards the east. Oh, I see. That's a very nice
פשט. Pshat. That I like. Because what gate is there? He's saying
we didn't discuss it, but there
were gates there.
Oh,
but
maybe there wasn't a gate. Yeah, that just gets you onto the
חיל. Chayil. I see. Yeah, yeah. So anyway, all right, so moving
on. So I don't know, did they have to go all the
way around? Or does it mean that they sort of retraced their
steps a little bit? They made like a
circle but not by going all around by more or less retracing
their steps. Okay, so then anyway, let's take a look.
חוץ ממי שאירע בו דבר שהוא מקיף לשמאל. Chutz MiMi She'ira Bo
Davar SheHu Makif LeSmol. Except if something happens to
somebody then he then he goes to the left rather than going
to the right. What do you mean to
get in, you mean?
No, no, which means
which means that and this does make it sound very much like
if you wanted to normally do it after you went you had
to keep on going all the way around because then it's saying
if something happens to somebody and he had to rush out, we'll
say in a minute what happened to them, then you don't keep
on moving to your right, you go back to your left and
there it sounds like you actually do retrace your steps. Okay? So
that's going back to your right though. No, because you're not turning
to your right, you're like I see. And this way you keep
on
moving,
yeah, that's what it says. Okay, anyway, so ומה לך מקיף לשמאל?
UMah Lecha Makif LeSmol? So they'd say to you, hey, what are
you doing? You're going in the wrong direction. So
happened to me sometimes, go to the early מנין Minyan and now
and then you hang around and then you're walking out of שול
Shul while everybody else is, what are you doing going in the
wrong
direction? Okay, so שאני אבל. SheAni Avel. So he says, oh no
no, I just heard that somebody died. I got to go home.
I'm an אבל. Avel.
You say heard at that
point? Seriously? Or they do this whole year of אבילות, Aveilut, in
which case people were מנחם Menachem them whole year?
I don't know, but why is he running out? He's running out
because אירעו דבר, Ira'o Davar, something occurred just now.
I
see. Why are you mucking? Why are you leaving? שאני אבל, SheAni
Avel, because I'm an אבל. Avel. So they would say to
him, השוכן בבית הזה ינחמך. HaShochein BaBayit HaZeh Yenachamecha. So they would
say השוכן בבית הזה יתן בליבך ha-shochen ba-bayit ha-ze yiten belibecha as
he swings he gets to בליבם ויקרבוך. belibam ve-yekarvucha. So the one
who dwells in this house should put in their hearts of those
who put you
in חרם cherem that
they should once again accept you. דברי רבי מאיר, divrei Rabbi Meir,
that’s what Rabbi Meir said. אמר לו רבי יוסי, amar lo Rabbi
Yose, so Rabbi Yose said, עשיתם כאילו עברו עליו את הדין. asitem
ke-ilu avru alav et ha-din. If you’re saying I hope they forgive
you, then that makes it like they did something wrong, like God
give it into their hearts to forgive you. It a little bit
suggests that they
were out of place, that they should reverse
themselves. אלא, ela, here’s what you should say: השוכן בבית הזה ha-shochen
ba-bayit ha-ze let the one who dwells in this house יתן בליבך
yiten belibecha give it in your heart ותשמע לדברי חבריך ve-tishma le-divrei
chaverecha and you should correct whatever it was you’ve been doing wrong
ואז ויקרבוך ve-az ve-yekarvucha and then they will you know will
accept you.
And this is why I’m thinking he’s also in אבילות. aveilut. He
didn’t just find out because it’s not like someone just found out.
So what is he doing getting up there?
Who? Why does he have to be מקיף makif there שמאל? smol?
Because that’s what I’m saying, like I think it’s a nice thing
that you know everyone this whole year of אבילות aveilut as long
as the guy’s excommunicated, they go out a different way.
That way people ask. Oh, I see, I see. No, that’s a
very good point. That’s a very good point. Okay, I accept that,
I think that you’re right. I think that’s a better פשט. pshat.
What Michael is saying is I was imagining that the reason he
was going the wrong way and the phrase אירע דבר ira davar
meant it occurred suddenly and he had to rush out, although it’s
hard then to imagine what does it mean it occurred suddenly that
he’s an אבל. avel. First of all, he’d be an אונן onen
not an אבל. avel. And what does it mean that he’s a
מנודה? menudeh? So Michael actually says, no, what it means is is
is is that he was already in that state, but he was
doing something different so that people would ask about it in order
to lead to them giving this תנחומי. tanchumei. Exactly, so that so
I accept you, that’s a much better פשט. pshat. I’m sorry, is
an אבל avel allowed on הר הבית?
Har HaBayit, Yeah, yeah, yeah.
No, I was imagining not that these people weren’t allowed but that
they were sort of had to take care of things, you know,
or they they were being rejected whatever the מנודה, menudeh, but I
think Michael’s absolutely correct. At least regarding the אבל avel that that
the phrase, first of all, he would be an אונן, onen, not
an אבל, avel, and it’s not clear why the מנודה menudeh all
of a sudden would have to leave. So I think you’re right,
I think it means, thank you Michael, that they were that they
were that they were in that state going up but they went
but that they made a point of being different where they left
so people would ask what’s going on.
Okay, and actually when I was in Israel I heard
that if I’m remembering this correctly, you just notice that there were
two שערי חולדה, sha’arei chulda, right? There’s this one, there’s that one.
And he and it could be that most of them went in
one way and the
אבל avel would go in and out the, you know.
Right, that’s what, well that is what I imagine, that you would
go to your right. Now whether you would go all the way
or you would go in the south, you’d go to your right,
whether you’d go all the way around like this and come out
like this, which is what it sounds like, although again then it’s
funny that this is so small, or
whether it means that you would somehow go like this, you know,
and come around this way but you’d still go out the other
way as opposed to him, he’s maybe turning this way and coming
out the same way. Absolutely,
absolutely. Okay, all right, משנה ג׳, mishna gimmel, let’s let’s get a
little further. לפנים ממנו, lifnim mimenu, also going from הר הבית inward,
you had סורג, soreg, the סורג, soreg, which was this little thing,
you know, which was sort of created the buffer zone before that
and the חיל, cheil, okay, the buffer zone. So this thing, yeah,
this, yeah, the most outermost thing fence or exactly. It’s called a
סורג soreg just like woven and it’s basically exactly like a crisscross
fence. Is it? Yeah, so like a fence of
wood. סורג גבוה י׳ טפחים soreg gavo’ah yud tefachim or ten טפחים
tefachim high, ושלש עשרה פרצות היו בו, u-shlosh esreh pertzot hayu vo,
there were thirteen breaks in the fence. I mean, anyway there had
to be openings in the fence so you could get through, but
those were intentional. There were thirteen places in which it was broken.
Why? שפרצום, she-peratzum, where were we, שפרצום מלכי יוון, she-peratzum malchei yavan,
and once again with the Greeks. So the Greeks actually when, you
know, in the story of חנוכה chanukah before the חשמונאים chashmonaim won
over, when they took over the temple, they broke through in thirteen
places. And for the reason they broke through is, and this goes
to the question before, is because you know there basically what that
fence indicated is
that was where no non-Jews could go beyond that fence. Okay, that
as I said before, the non-Jews were אסור assur in the חיל
cheil even before the עזרה. Azara, So basically they said, ‘Ha, you
know, you’re trying to keep us out,’ and they broke through that
fence in thirteen places. חזרו וגדרום, chazru u-gedarum, so they so they
sealed them up, וגזרו כנגדן י״ג השתחוויות. ve-gazru kenegdan yud gimmel hishtachavuyot.
And they said that opposite them thirteen prostrations, which what does it
mean? So some say every time you passed one of those breaks
you had to prostrate
yourself thirteen
times. No, the better explanation is each time that you pass one
of those breaks you would prostrate yourself to basically probably thank God
for having given us back the sovereignty of הר הבית and gotten
the Greeks out and so on. Okay, so that’s why in these
pictures they have those breaks. Okay, לפנים ממנו, lifnim mimenu, yes? Do
you think of any connection between that thirteen and like thirteen attributes?
Yeah, obviously thirteen is a pretty Significant number, right,
so but maybe that they did it also to
be symbolic and
so they're trying to pick something symbolic, yeah, could be. לפנימי ממנו
החיל. Lifnimi mimenu HaChel. So now the space between that and the
עזרה is called the חיל, Chel, which we mentioned before, עשר אמות,
eser amot, it's ten אמות amot wide, like fifteen feet. ושתים עשרה
מעלות היו שם, Ushteim esrei maalot hayu sham, and there were twelve
steps. רום מעלה חצי אמה ושלוך חצי אמה, Rom maalah chatzi amah
veshioch chatzi amah, each step went a half אמה amah high and
went in a half אמה, amah, so it was about three quarters
of a foot high and in three quarters of a foot. So
if you think about that and you had fifteen steps, so fifteen
times half, twelve? I'm sorry, not my day. Twelve steps, so twelve
times a half, a half אמה, amah, is six אמות. amot. So
the steps took up more than half of the space. The whole
space was ten אמות, amot, so there were four אמות amot of
nothing and then you know
of ground and then there were steps going for the remaining six
אמות. amot. So the actual entrance to the עזרה even once you're
on הר הבית, you'd have to go through the חיל Chel and
then walk up the steps before getting to the עזרה itself, which
is a nice idea. You don't go straight into the עזרה, you
have to walk up to the עזרה, literally מעלין בקודש. maalin bakodesh.
Exactly. Okay. כל המעלות היו שם רום מעלה חצי אמה ושלוך חצי
אמה, Kol hamaalot hayu sham rom maalah chatzi amah veshioch chatzi amah,
all the steps that were there were half אמה amah high and
a half אמה amah like deep, in, you know, חוץ משל אולם,
chutz mishel ulam, except for the one of going into the אולם,
ulam, which we will discuss later. כל הפתחים שהיו שם גבוהים עשרים
אמה ורחבן עשר אמות, Kol haptachim shehayu sham gevohim esrim amah verochban
eser amot,
all of the doors and the gates or whatever were twenty אמה
amah high, thirty feet, which is pretty huge, which is why those
pictures you see like you know it's huge. חוץ משל אולם, chutz
mishel ulam, except for the אולם, ulam, which was basically even higher,
we will see all that. כל הפתחים שהיו שם היו להם דלתות,
Kol haptachim shehayu sham hayu lahem delatot, all of the all of
the openings had doors in them.
חוץ משל אולם? chutz mishel ulam? No, the doors like the main
gates. No, you would close a gate, wouldn't just be an open
gate. חוץ משל אולם, chutz mishel ulam, except for the אולם, ulam,
because the אולם, ulam, when we say פתחים ptachim we don't mean
the actual door. First we're describing the
פתח, petach, the space. Okay, so all these things the פתח petach
was twenty אמה amah high, thirty feet by ten, huge, and all
of them had a door in the פתח. petach. You mean like
a gate. A gate, as I said, a gate, okay, except for
the אולם ulam because the אולם ulam had a curtain. Okay, the
אולם ulam again was the structure right before it fed into the
היכל, Heichal, that had was higher and it didn't have a door,
it had a curtain. Remember we said before that the כהן Kohen
came out after the קטורת ketoret and he opened the curtain and
then all the כהנים came in to do their השתחויה? hishtachavaya? So
that was a curtain which was in the
front
of the אולם. ulam.
Okay, where were we? כל השערים שהיו שם היו להם שקופות, Kol
hashearim shehayu sham hayu lahem shkofot, all of the gates, all of
the arches, whatever, gates
there were they had lintels. Lintels? Lentils, I'm sorry, lentil soup. חוץ
משל טדי, chutz mishel Taddi, except for טדי Taddi שהיו שם שתי
אבנים מוטות זו על גב זו. shehayu sham shtei avanim mutot zo
al gav zo. So we'd have an architect to tell us the
different structure, but basically the first one was just like a straight
you know door frame, so a straight lintel. The other one was
more it sounds like Roman or Greek or whatever, was two you
know stones which were you know made like a V, okay, and
that that was the top of the...
Is that what this shape is around the...? Around the what? Around
what we're talking about. Is that what these
are? These U-shapes?
Those?
I guess. I mean those, yeah, I mean those are the... but
just... no, but that... yes, but those are like the balconies. Here
he's talking about the opening itself. The opening... what was the shape
of the you know of the opening? So was it a simple
rectangular shape or at the top it actually came to more like
a V-top at the top? Okay, the basic just whole opening, all
right.
כל השערים שהיו שם נשתנו להיות של זהב, Kol hashearim shehayu sham
nishtanu lihyot shel zahav, all of the all of the gates there
and presumably here it means the doors of the gate were changed
to gold, meaning they weren't always gold but they eventually replaced them
with gold when they had the wealth. חוץ משער ניקנור, chutz mishar
Nikanor, except for the gate of ניקנור, Nikanor, מפני שנעשה בהם נס,
mipnei shenaasah bahem nes, because of the miracle we mentioned, they didn't
want to replace it, so even so it was not gold but
they left it. ויש אומרים, Veyeish omrim, some said, מפני שנחושתן מצהיב,
mipnei shenechushtan mazhiv,
because the copper you know shined like gold, looked gold, so you
know you want to make everything beautiful, but if everybody thinks it's
gold you don't need to waste money.
So although normally we say אין עני במקום עשירות. ein ani bimekom
ashirut. So some say it wasn't because of the miracle but because
it looked gold enough. Okay, we will continue tomorrow.